Quite how they got the tickets, but they did well to do so.
And they're here.
We're waiting for a big step up in class from Paolo Espinoza Sanchez, bronze medalist of the World Championships last year.
Naomi Baki of Italy, born in Hungary, but now representing Italy.
Julia Prokopchuk of the Ukraine.
Now the second of the Canadians, again looking for a slightly better performance.
She'll need it if she wants to make it into the top 12, which is where we will be at the end of this session.
And now full of beans, full of life and full of words.
Katie Bell of the USA.
Watch her preparation for every dive.
She'll be having a little chat or a chunter to herself.
Mai Nagagawa of Japan.
into the last seven.
Now, this is the order in which they will dive five rounds of dives.
Remember in the women's Yulia Coltanova.
Those are the two Chinese.
It's Yabang Hu.
Women's 10 meter platform semi-final.
They're just introducing the 18 who made it through from an original list of 26.
Sadie from a British point of view.
No representation.
Stacey Powell didn't make it through.
Naughty Monique Gladding.
She was 19th last night, so she missed out on that last remaining place.
Christian Stur of Germany had an exceptional performance last night.
Leon Taylor, as ever, is alongside me.
The 10 meter
Synchro silver medalist from 2004 in Athens.
I think it's safe to say Leon, the standard last night left a little bit to be desired.
Yeah, it seemed to me that not many of these ladies wanted to make it through to this semi-final.
But Shen Ruolin, the Olympic champion, only 15 years old, four years ago in Beijing, tops the field or top the field by a huge margin by the end of the proceedings last night.
it's a tough program for these young ladies they are on again and they didn't finish until late last night they were still diving close to 10 pm obviously back to the olympic village have something to eat to rest try and turn your adrenaline down to get some sleep and then get back up early this morning to come in and practice your dives from the mighty 10 meter platform there towering above all the other diving boards this is the dive order once again and of course
The girls do five dives.
Each of those dives counts and it's the total score, which means you make it through or you don't.
Top 12 go through to this evening's final, so it's a lot of diving in a short space of time.
Who is the fittest and who can hold it together mentally?
Last night, lots of faltering.
Will we see the same this morning?
I think we might see one or two.
What about Monique Gladding?
It was a surprise to some actually she even competed last night because she had a quite serious injury.
She did, what an absolute shame.
Monique Gladding finishing 19th, Stacey Powell 20th so they're both reserve one and reserve two but none of the ladies ahead of them have been injured in the meantime and so they're watching on the poolside thinking what if.
Monique Gladding of course hitting her head on the diving board in Russia only just over a year ago
And, yeah, fortunately, knocking herself out, sunk to the bottom of the pool, rescued by her teammate Nicholas Robinson Baker.
A truly dramatic story, an inspirational story, how she came back and made the Olympic Games team at the age of 31, her first Olympic Games.
Such a shame to see her not featuring today in the semi-final alongside Stacey Powell as well, having a tough day in the diving pool, meaning reserve one and reserve two.
What a shame.
Right, so just say how this works in case you're new to diving and haven't seen our coverage up to this point.
The marks will appear on your screen.
All the marks that have lines through them will not count towards the total.
In other words, the top and bottom marks are discarded.
The three in the middle will be taken as their marks.
and they will be multiplied by the degree of difficulty.
Now, in most cases, in the first round, it will be 3.0.
We might go down into the twos, we do go down into the twos.
We only go as high in the women's as opposed to the men's, Leon, as 3.3.
Yeah, let me just explain.
The degree of difficulty is assigned to each of the dives, and it depends on how difficult the dive is to how high the degree of difficulty is.
And in this competition, we see ranging from 2.7 up to a highest of 3.3.
Now I can explain that as it goes on, but what you're looking at, seven execution judges, the two highest and two lowest marks are discounted, so they have lines through them.
This is so we average out any, well, any amount of subjectivity to leave three marks.
Those are then, as Bob said, totaled and multiplied by the degree of difficulty to give the total for that particular dive.
The girls this morning have to do five different dives in five different directions and they have six directions to choose from, if you will.
Forwards, which is self-explanatory.
Backwards, which is also self-explanatory.
Inwards, which is where you stand backwards, spin forwards towards the diving board.
The reverse, which is the opposite, which is where you stand forwards, jump away from the diving board and spin backwards towards it.
And the twist group, which is where you rotate longitudinally as well.
That's really complicated.
And of course, the sixth group, which is available on the platform, is the handstand, the armstand group.
And some girls choose to do that.
And my co-commentator, Bob Ballard, gets ever so nervous when the girls or the boys do handstands from the 10 meter platform.
Now they made it easy for you this morning in as much as the first 10 divers will all do exactly the same dive.
So you get a chance to compare and contrast how good or bad or indifferent the dives are.
So the first 10 all opting for a forward three and a half somersaults in the pike position.
As you see on your screen, 3.0 degree of difficulty.
So the marks that count will be multiplied by that
for all of the first 10 divers.
First up is Kim of the People's Republic of Korea.
Well, she was probably one of the surprises making it through, just scraping in in 18th spot, but that's a very steady opening dive.
What are you looking for?
Right on the end of the diving board, do you notice a towel on the end of the diving board there?
That's just preference for the divers.
It is actually a non-slip surface on the platform, but some divers prefer probably from a comfort point of view to put a wet towel down to add to some grip, but that's a solid start from Kim.
Yeah, sixty-three is a mark you will probably see quite a bit off because the judges tend to go for that mid-range seven multiplied by the degree of difficulty gives you sixty-three.
There are a few divers who are waiting to up their game considerably and here is one of them.
The first of the Canadians you'll see Roslyn Filion.
Second up of eighteen.
Remember, we reduced them to twelve for the final later today.
Again, the four, three and a half.
Yeah, she's a little bit off her game.
She certainly was last night.
This young lady won a bronze medal only last week in the synchronised 10 metre event with her partners also in this contest.
Well, it could be doing squeezing into her pike shape a little bit more there.
It didn't look very neat and tidy.
She's a little bit loose as she entered the water.
Looks a little bit tired, actually.
There we go.
See the divers punching a hole into the water there, spreading their hands as they go in and sucking down all the air with them to try and do their rip entry, which is a splashless entry.
Not quite as good as the opening dive.
61.50 for Filion.
Now here comes Maria Curio.
Oh, Maria not quite completing the dive.
You can see entering short to vertical as she hits the water.
I think she needed an 11 meter platform to make this one safely.
This, of course, only a 10 meter platform.
Look how low she finishes to the water.
The water would hit her on her chest and then the top of her thighs, throwing up quite a lot of splash.
That'll be the lowest scoring dive so far.
Early stages.
But for this young German diver to make it through, she would need to be at the top of her game, and that's a little bit off.
quite a bit off unfortunately from her point of view.
So already having to play catch up forty-nine point five zero with four and a half and five sprinkled across there and she is a way off the pace early stages.
Now, Kim Jin Ok of People's Republic of Korea, semi-finalist in Beijing and also the last two World Championships.
So she's emulated what she's done in her last three big meets.
Can she go one better this time?
Well, it's really good.
The divers are looking to enter the water.
Fantastic support from the teammates looking to enter the water completely vertically with no splash.
And if you're doing that, you're going to get eights and upwards from the judges.
I think that's the best forward three and a half we've seen this morning from Kim.
Squeezing into the pipe shape.
Heavily taped on her ankles and calves there.
Lots of these divers held together by sticky tape and this is one of them.
That's good.
Very good.
70.50.
A couple of eights and a 7.5 to count towards the total.
Times three and you get the picture and you get the calculation.
Now Brittany Viola who has a big support team including her dad.
Who's a major league baseball legend.
Frank.
And the Americans going with a four, three and a half as indeed all the previous four have done.
Yeah, just letting the dive run over.
Brittany really attacking the takeoff there, cranking up the rotation, which is well, exactly what you want to be doing.
Have a little bit of a nap there.
Might be a bit tired from a late finish last night.
Here we go.
Squeezing into the pike shape.
All looks good so far.
Just out a little bit late from the rotation.
Rolls over a touch.
Still get over 65 points which will keep her in contention.
I'm surprised to see her this low down finish.
She did make one mistake though last night to move her down the pack.
Yeah, we expect her to move up as well.
67.50.
It's a solid opening dive for her that puts her in second place for the time being.
Now, the big surprise to me last night was this lady, Paolo Espinosa-Sanchez.
Bronze medalist last year.
Never really got going in a program.
Perhaps she will on this occasion.
Yep, see it's still not as good as we would expect from Paola Espinosa.
Multiple medallist at world level and of course Olympic medallist only last week in the synchronised 10 metre platform.
Here just arching as she goes into the water giving the impression the dive is further over than it actually was.
So over from vertical splash comes towards us there.
She'll only get sevens on that, better than her prelim but still not as good as we expect.
I'm going for her to come to life and show what she really is all about.
She was so impressive last year at the Worlds, but so far we haven't seen anything like that kind of form from her.
Now the Hungarian born, Italian representing Naomi Bakke.
Again, same dive.
Oh, again, Naomi just letting the dive run over a vertical.
You can see the sprays there from the side of the pool.
It's actually like a hosepipe spraying water just onto the surface.
The reason for this is so you disturb the surface of the water so the divers can see exactly where they want to land.
So if the water was still, you could see the bottom of the pool, which is actually 5.8 metres further away.
So the sprays disturbing the water so the divers know exactly when to grab their hands and try and enter the water.
She might be a bit disturbed by that score there actually.
58.50 not quite what she would have hoped for.
Remember it's five rounds and plenty of time for reparation.
Iulia Rogopchuk of Ukraine.
Right down to diver number 11.
We'll see exactly the same.
She's diver number six.
And there's that four, three and a half again.
Oh, that's very tidy.
She needs to squeeze into her pike shape a little bit to get most marks from the judges.
There should be no daylight in between the thighs and the chest.
And as you can see there, you can almost drive a small car through that gap.
It needs to be a lot tighter, but she does a very good entry on the end of the dive there.
Yeah, it's an interesting technique.
Normally the divers wrap around the backs of the carves with the forearms.
Yulia there holding on with her hands.
That's very difficult.
You need an incredible amount of arm strength, but she gets eights on it.
She does.
72 puts her in the lead.
A reminder to you, the judges do not see the replays that you see.
They judge it purely on what they see in real time.
So if we see anything on the replays that they don't, it will be because they only get one look and we get several.
Megan Benfito second of the Canadians with her opening dive There you can see the difference in the pike shape there between Megan and Lulia Squeezing in so there was no daylight in between her body and her thighs look at this squeezing into that tight pike shape Completing the rotations very comfortably just letting the dive roll over as she goes in so she won't get any eight seven and a halfs I think on this one
And I expect this lady to feature in this evening's final.
Yeah, it'd be a big surprise if she didn't.
A lot of Canadians here to support her, both at the pool and watching on TV, I know, in the UK.
So 7.5 has crossed the board, times three, gives you 67.50.
Now, Katie's going to have a chat.
Here we go.
Preparation, has a smile, has a chat.
She'll count herself in.
And ready to go.
Oh, it seems to work though.
She's got more moves than the chess player.
Up there, moving around, quite nervous, talking to herself, doing what she needs to do.
But it certainly worked for her yesterday in the prelims.
And that's a better start here.
Just a little bit over a vertical, but a splashless entry.
This could get some eights from the judges and probably put her top of the leaderboard so far in this competition.
Great start there from Katie Bell.
I think we warmed to it.
Certainly the crowd have.
Just for her little idiosyncrasies before she dives.
73.50 puts Katie Bell into the lead.
Now, my Nakagawa of Japan.
She had a very good pre-lance with a very small degree of difficulty in comparison.
Oh, now did you hear that?
So what happened there?
She's doing the inward and she actually smacks her feet on the board.
I heard a sound.
Now, if the judges saw that as well, you'll see on the replay here.
donk with her toes that isn't going to hurt but it does well it doesn't throw her because the dyes very good now if the judges see it they're going to cane her on the points so they're going to really penalize because of course you're not going to hit the diving board and because it made a loud donk sound i think the judges will all spot that well they should they're olympic judges let's see well yes they do they've all spotted it that would have got eights if it didn't so they've decided to take off the right amount of points
Alright, 4.5 to 6.5 I think is quite a differential but obviously that's the reason we have it evened out in the middle so we don't get too much of a widespread of marks.
So we've seen threes, we've seen 2.7 now we're upping the ante a little bit.
This will be a 3.1 and the first of our arm stands.
There's a lot of ooh and aahing I can hear in the background from the crowd.
Yes, so impressive, isn't it?
Could you imagine just standing on the edge of a 10-metre platform anyway?
But let alone doing a handstand.
Seems pretty normal to me.
I used to do it every day.
But here we go.
For those of you at home, look how impressive this is.
And that's a beautiful dive there.
That'll put her straight into the lead.
She did this in the prelims yesterday.
opening up on probably her best dive and what confidence does it take to open up your Olympic competition in a handstand?
Well she threw herself a bit like a catapult there and it worked very effectively.
8.5s and 8s and obviously a slightly higher degree of difficulty gives her the extra marks too.
77.50.
First of the two Chinese now, Hu Yudan, 16 years of age.
Let's see this more like it who you done was well a little bit off by her standards last night and Watching her in training.
She doesn't seem to be as sharp as I've seen her before She is only 16, but she is an absolutely phenomenal diver and that is just a little bit off the pace It'll only get seven and a half's now from this young lady I've seen her disappear into the water for nines and tens on this dive and that is
back from the eight ball right across the board seven point five up to eight point five will count to a total which is sixty nine for who goes into fifth place in round one now from australia didn't do the synchro ten last week as we thought she might she was uh going to second place in their trials but here she is individual melissa woo
Yeah, very steady from Melissa Wu last night in the prelims.
One of the few divers who were diving consistently.
And I'm sure she'll put in a consistent performance here in the semifinal.
Again, opting for the towel.
That's just a comfort thing.
It is wet to give you a little bit more grip or maybe not.
Anyway, it's the divers preference.
Needs to be in with the color and the branding.
So the towels are provided because some divers like to use them.
And Melissa Wu is one and she ends up pretty good after a first round dive.
Yeah, it goes into joint second place, 73.50.
So nice solid opening from the Australian, four points behind the Russian Coltanova.
Now, Brittany Brobin, second of the Australians, 16 years of age with her reverse two and a half somersaults with tug, slight variance for you, and only 2.7 attached to this one.
Oh, what a dive.
I was expecting that.
This is her favourite dive.
She tends to open with it and it's an impressive one.
So this is the reverse.
This is where you stand forwards and jump away from the diving board, spinning backwards.
Dangerous.
Impressive.
And that is very well executed.
This could see some nines.
and it certainly should.
Only 16 years old and wow, she is performing exceptionally well in her first Olympic Games.
And a very safe distance from the board as well which is good to see.
Yes, we've got a few people getting much more close than we would like but she has achieved what she needed to do with that opening dive and it's very impressive.
71.55 puts her in with the top pack in fifth place.
Now this I think was a surprise because it's a low tariff
program that Kristen Sturr has, but she did it to perfection last night pretty much.
2.8 inward 2.5 somersaults.
She'll perform this in the pike position, which Leon will explain after you've seen it.
Yeah, if you remember in the prelim, this was her weakest dive.
She actually left herself quite a lot to do and then, you know, cruised through as other girls were faltering, moving away from the diving board, missing her feet, unlike Nakagawa, who tipped her toes, Christine Storm, moving a safer distance away from the diving board.
It is tricky to miss the diving board because you're obviously in the pike position, which is folding at the hips and keeping it straight through the knees.
There we go.
Those marks are OK, but less than 60 points.
She'll be off the pace.
Yeah, the degree of difficulty reducing her options in terms of points she can achieve.
And that's going to put her down relatively near the bottom.
And three, ten, and synchro.
Very busy girl.
Oh, she was on fire yesterday, wasn't she?
In the preliminaries.
There are teammates cheering her on.
Fantastic support for all of the divers here today.
and look at this pike shape it's beautiful she seems to have such amazing flexibility in the hamstrings and in the lower back that she can almost get her chin on her ankles in the pike shape which is very impressive it makes the rotations even easier she could do is squeezing into her pike shape a little bit more but i think she's rotating that fast she was a little bit nervous to squeeze in too much and she
starts with a good score once again.
67.50 remember these divers have had a very short recovery time they're still competing about 12 hours ago now the outstanding diver in the preliminaries winning it by a long way Chen Ruolin of China world champion
Oh, maybe Chen didn't quite get to bed early enough last night.
Well, she didn't have a choice because she was still in here until 10 p.m.
But that's a little bit off for this young lady, Olympic champion at the age of 15.
Here she is four years on and hasn't really been challenged in this event since.
The occasional competition that has been a bit more closely run, but that's a little bit off the mark there for Shenmue Lin.
That's going to put her, well, she's not going to be top after the first round, which is unusual.
Although we must build a little caveat to that, the Chinese sometimes get a little bit marked up.
Perhaps she has been on this occasion.
8.5.
73.50 for the Olympic gold medalist from last time around the age of 15, now 19.
So round one is completed.
And these are the scores.
Remember, top 12 go through.
Bottom six get discarded.
Kaltenova, a very positive start for her.
Katie Bell, Chen Ruolin, and Melissa Wu all together at the moment.
If the competition were to stop, Paolo Espinosa-Sanchez would be the last one to go through, and we would lose Roslyn Finion, among others, below that line of 12.
26 down to 18, and then down to 12 tonight.
So just to explain the differences in some of the dives that we're seeing.
So the girls have to do five dives and five different dives.
They have to cover five different groups.
So basically go in different directions.
And you've seen most of them now.
Forwards, backwards, inwards, which is where you stand backwards, spin forwards, reverse, which is where you stand forwards and spin backwards.
And also the twist, which is where you rotate along the longitudinal axis as well.
This is the inwards coming up now for Kim.
In with three and a half somersaults with Tuck and the degree of difficulty is the highest we have seen in the competition so far.
3.2 remember, top marks, three that count will be multiplied by the degree of difficulty.
Oh, she does very well.
Very well, Kim.
Lots of the ladies were a bit here and there in the prelim.
Kim made it through, squeezing in.
Her hair is quite close to the diving board.
In fact, it may have even touched the diving board, so that's a little bit too close for comfort.
This is the dive that Monique Gladding had her accident on, and you can see how accidents can happen.
Having to stand backwards, spin forwards towards it.
The judges didn't think it was too close, though.
They've marked her fairly.
Well, I've got to say, it was close enough for me.
Too close.
Sevens and 67.20.
Remember, the middle marks the ones that count.
Top two, bottom two, discarded.
The middle ones will count.
And the degree of difficulty is the multiplication.
That's how we arrive at 67.20.
Now, 14th place after round one.
She doesn't want to be there for very long.
Roseline Fillon.
And a back three and a half, here's a bigger dive indeed, 3.3.
Oh, she struggled on that in the prelims and she struggled a little bit again.
You can tell from her first dive that she looked a little bit maybe fatigued, a little bit tired, which I'm not surprised about.
Anyway, this is a big dive.
She needs to squeeze into her tuck shape a little bit more.
Ending up short of vertical with a lower back arch and throwing up quite a bit of splash.
It should get over 60 points.
It was better than the prelims.
So all is not over for this young lady, but you can just see by her body language there that she is finding it tough out there today.
Frustrating for her.
She started at 61.5.
She's gone down to 61.05.
That was a higher degree of difficulty on that dive as well.
Here's Maria Curio with her arm stand, which gives me a chance to tell you that she struck her head against the 10 meter tower, lost consciousness and fell into the water just over two years ago, suffering lacerations and concussion.
So similar kind of story to
Monique Gladding last year.
She was back on the diving board a month later.
Can you believe how brave some of these divers are?
Here comes her armstand.
It's a big one, 2.3.2.
Armstand back, double somersault, one and a half twist.
We will see one more intricate than this later on.
Yeah, oohs and ahs from the crowd.
And very, very impressive.
Having to show a steady arm stand balance to the judges before you take off.
Flicking off there into the one and a half twist, completing the dive.
She's straight up and down on that.
That'll get over 70 points, seven and a half.
There we go, lifting up.
Interesting, one foot at a time.
Elbows are bent.
That's incredible arm strength.
Here she goes.
Look at that overhead view.
Any of you fancy that at home?
Probably not.
No.
Thank you for asking but I'll I'll decline that offer.
Very kind of it is.
Seventy-two from and uh she and have a bit of a battle themselves for that second place as it stands.
On to Kim Jin Ok of the People's Republic of Korea.
Well to
And she's going in with three and a half somersaults, 3.2.
Oh, she's done well there.
It looked like there was a trap door on the end of the 10 meter diving board just as she took off.
Instead of springing up through the ankles, she seems to move her hips back and skip backwards, which does mean that she's a safe distance from the diving board, which is good, but it does make the dive more difficult to control.
However, Kim here does a fantastic job with a trap door takeoff.
Well done.
And the exits are here, here, and here.
67.20.
Sevens for Kim.
And that puts, temporarily at least, into first place ahead of the other Kim.
Brittany Viola with a big support team.
That's Mum.
Mum didn't have a good night's sleep either by the looks of things.
Arm stand back, double somersault, one and a half twists, 3.2.
You've seen this one before.
He's executed pretty well.
What's the noise in the crowd as they get into that upright position?
Oh, it's just a little bit short of vertical as she goes in there.
Brittany did all the hard work.
I mean, imagine how challenging it is.
All the blood rushes to your head.
Then you need to flick off and then you hurtle towards the water, hitting the water at nearly 40 miles an hour.
And yes, a lot going on.
1.6 seconds it takes to complete the dive.
Viola just a little short.
She went into the water there, the water hitting her on the chest and the front of the legs.
Splash going back towards the diving board, spreading the arms there, trying to get in without any splash.
A little bit under par.
Yeah, chick flicks for you in the diving this morning.
Sixty point eight zero for Brittany.
That's not going to help her cause a great deal.
She's slipping down the pecking order and third at the moment now.
Come on, Paola.
Let's see what you can really do, Paola.
Espinosa Sanchez of Mexico.
Three point three back, three and a half somersaults.
Classy act.
Can she show us and underline why that's the case?
No I think you should keep quiet when Paola's diving, you were doing this last night in the prelims and this young lady is an exceptional diver but we haven't seen it since last week in the synchronised diving event.
Look how high she is, she cruises this dive, kicks out but she should be out of that dive earlier.
Over she goes, lots of splash, enough splash.
Well, mini wave, mini surfboards.
Time for some surfing already.
She has given herself a lot to do on the basis of that dive now.
She slipped.
Yeah, like last night, she was 18th at one point.
Looked like she wouldn't make it.
Only 12 today.
Not that comfort blanket of those six places today.
She is in the bottom place at the moment and struggling, which I find amazing.
Naomi Bacchi of Italy back two and a half somersaults.
Only 2.9 degree of difficulty on this.
She'll perform it in the pike position.
Oh, that's a bat around the back of the head there.
She didn't look back with her chin and reach back with the arms.
And let me tell you, when the water hits you that hard around the back of the head, that does not tickle.
Oh my goodness.
This is why divers get so many neck injuries.
Oh, she goes in.
Interesting, Paola showing you the backward three and a half, which carries a 3.3 degree of difficulty.
This is backward two and a half in the pike position.
Easier, only 2.9.
So it needed to be better than that from this young Italian.
Well, we're just having a little kind of wobble here with a few of the divers.
This happened last night where one seems to trigger another, triggers another.
Needs somebody just to steady the ship and get back on target and back on track.
Maybe it's Iulia Prokopchuk, the person who can do that.
It is in with three and a half, three point two fifth after round one.
Oh it's pretty good straight up and down just a little bit too much splash but it's 3.2 degree of difficulty and as long as she's steady she's got 72 on her first round dive I don't think she'll be as high as that on second round dive just throwing up a little bit too much splash but she'll get over 60s mid 60s probably and that will be good enough to keep her
Well, middle of the pack, which is where she needs to be to make it through to the top twelve going through.
Yeah, sixty-four, not as good as our opening dive, which is seventy-two.
That was a high degree of difficulty this time, of course, and she goes for the time being at least into second, but she won't remain there for too long.
Now, equal ninth after round one, still not quite in the groove.
3.3 back three and a half somersaults once more in the tuck position for Canada's Megan Benfito.
Oh, she does very well.
She made a little bit of a mess of this in the prelims.
That made it more difficult for her to finish in the top of the field.
And she did a good fight back.
And this is much more like it.
Squeezing into the tuck shape.
Tuck shape bending at the hips and at the knees.
Hanging onto the shins with both hands.
Squeezing into almost a little ball.
You can only see where you've been on this dive.
So you have to predict where to place your feet.
Which she does perfectly and plonks it right on her head.
75.9.
Good dive.
Yeah, good dive.
Puts her in the lead for the time being.
now the pocket rocket from Columbus USA 24 years old 6 stone 11 dripping wet with lots of words to add who is she talking to I think she's talking to herself or us maybe now what's the counting gonna be sometimes it's five six seven eight sometimes it's one two three reverse two and a half
oh she's just well it's such a tricky dive this is the reverse two and a half she's electing to do it in the pike position which is 2.9 degree of difficulty she did it in the tuck position it would be only 2.7 so you get pretty close with your toes and she was hanging on into a pike shape too long there you can see the dive goes over let's check out this overhead camera shot oh it's enough to make you well i'm not sure but anyway she goes over
Too much splash.
56 points.
She won't be happy with that.
Six point fives across the board.
Fifty six point five five and that just knocks her down a peg or two.
She was second equal after round one.
waiting for something really to come to life.
Maybe my Nakagawa could be that person.
No, Nakagawa obviously lost her confidence and whenever Bob says watch this diver, they seem to go, oh, hang on a second, that's too much pressure.
Anyway, Nakagawa hitting her feet on the first opening dive, which put her into 18th here.
well what a shame all the aerial work was fantastic spinning you know was well it's all good what an absolute shame she should just come out now but instead she comes out a little bit later rolls over onto her back and i think that'll be her campaign good is over with two poor dives just incredible how many divers in both the preliminaries and this are not spotting their entries 48
exactly for the Japanese and yeah we may not see her back for the final on Thursday evening.
Yulia Koltanova, great start.
What's she got now?
Oh she sneaks that in, she's very very low on the water.
This is a tough dive, 3.3 degree of difficulty and she's a tough diver.
Here we go, jumping up as high as you can, squeezing into that tuck shape, waiting, waiting, waiting, and then she pops out with just, oh, just about enough time to spare.
And she's done very well there.
because that could have been a lot shorter than it was.
She managed to keep the splashdown very good indeed.
Judges think this 69.30 remember all the marks without lines through them count towards the total multiplied by the degree of difficulty and there's people tuning in all the time so that's why we're reminding you so sorry if you're a bit fed up with our explanations.
Hu Yidan 16 from China in with three and a half semisaults with tuck with 3.2 in degree of difficulties and ballet dancers
posture there.
Wow, there's not much of Hu Yu Dan and I'm always surprised when I see her enter the water with that much splash.
I wonder how she manages that.
Normally we're used to her disappearing into the water.
Here we go, all looks good so far and then just goes loose through the body and that's where all the splash gets thrown up.
The aerial work is spot on.
She comes out the dive, piking out really class.
He doesn't lock out the elbows on the finish and therefore gets
Let's have a look.
Doesn't quite, yeah, doesn't quite lock out the elbows and then gets like a earthquake which goes right through the body, hence the splash.
Look, holding the back of her head.
She's hurt her neck.
Oh.
Coach, have me a word or two, which probably won't be any consolation for the Chinese.
As we move to the Australian Melissa Wu.
Now, here comes the 3.2.
We will see a 3.3, by the way, very soon.
Arm stand back, double somersault, one and a half twists.
Oh, just entering the water short of vertical, which means that Melissa probably won't get more than sixes on that.
Just needed a bit more of a pop off the top there.
So I needed to push with her arms a little bit stronger just to give herself a little bit more clearance going in.
It's a very neat dive until we get into the water and then just you can see the water moving back towards the diving board.
Yeah.
Still waiting for somebody to take this competition by the scruff of the neck and nobody yet is doing so.
Wu with sixty-four puts her into fifth place.
Now here comes her teammate.
The younger of the two Australians.
Sixteen years of age is Brittany and it's a inward three and a half with
Oh yes, well she nailed her first round dive, 71 points on a very low degree of difficulty, 2.7.
This is 3.2 and that is the best we've seen of the competition so far.
What a dive from this young lady, only 16 years old and acting like she's been in the Olympic Games before.
This could get high 70s, not sure whether the judges
will be awake enough to go higher than that but let's wait and see.
Well they like it and we like it.
81.60 for Brittany who has to travel two hours backwards and forwards in Brisbane to do her diving up at 4.15 every morning so I don't think an early start is worrying her too much.
Christian Sturr of Germany just upping her
here.
3.2 now for a back two and a half somersaults with one and a half twists and she's currently in 15th place so need to move up three to be back tonight.
Yeah, very, very clean entry into the water.
Even though her aerial work is not as good as some of the other divers.
Stoya quite weak in comparison with her take-offs, which means the dive finishes a little bit lower than some of her fellow athletes.
But look at that entry into the water.
They'll get seven and a halves.
She'd get even more if she was able to jump a little bit higher.
That's three point two.
It'd be a good total score.
Yep, seventy-two.
Seventy-two it is.
With seven point five times the degree of difficulty.
Nobody yet landing in those Olympic rings yet.
If they're landing in the Olympic rings, they've gone a bit too far.
So, a bit of a marker for you.
Pandela Pang of Malaysia.
Doing well in the prelims.
Here she goes with dive number two in the semifinal.
Back two and a half
She nailed it in the prelims, and she's done it exactly the same again.
There we are.
The coach is capturing every single dive for post-diving analysis.
This is what you did well.
This is what you could do better next time.
Panda Lella, beautiful diving, coming out of the dive very, very early.
So only 2.9 degree of difficulty.
So it needed to be nails.
I think she'll get a bag full of nines for this.
And so she should.
Superb diving.
Spectacular.
Yeah, she's good.
She was good last night.
She's good today.
Seventy-five point four zero for Pandela and that will lift her up the standings.
A lot of people concentrating and wondering whether they'll be back tonight.
Seven World Series victories this year for this lady, Jen Rulin, the Olympic and world champion in with three and a half somersaults with
And into the lead she goes.
Wow.
People wondering, shaky first round dive from the Olympic champion.
Will she come out all guns blazing in round number two?
The answer is yes.
This will go sailing over 80 points.
Beautiful entry into the water.
Look at that overhead shot.
Very strong.
Safe distance from the diving board.
Technically, nigh on perfect.
Great dive.
Hard after the prelim to see anybody beating her.
And on the evidence of that, hard to see her to be topping her in the semis either.
Chen Ruolin 83.20, last to go in round two.
So a lot of cogitation and contemplation going on between the 18 divers as they try and work out what they need to do to qualify.
Not a problem for Chen or indeed for Brobin at the moment.
Down to nine, fairly secure.
It gets a little bit more wobbly and a little bit more anxious.
Certainly for Brittany Viola, who's not in there.
Roslyn Filion, who's not in there.
And look at that.
How that's Espinosa Sanchez.
Bronze medalist from last year at the World Championship 16th after round two.
On to round three.
It's very congested around there.
Everybody trying to find their little place to have a little
Maybe a little nap.
Listen to some music.
Get back in the concentration zone because a long time between dives for them.
Not as long obviously as it was in the semis in the fight in the prelims but in the semis they have to wait 20 minutes before they get a chance to go again.
Here's Kim Boon Hyang of the People's Republic of Korea.
This is the bigger of the arm stand back somersaults.
It's a triple in the tuck position 3.3.
This is worth
Oh, Kim's having the meat of her life, wow.
Only just getting into this semi-final and that is three out of three and that's her most difficult dive.
Here we are in the handstand, the donkey kick as it's sometimes known, flicking in, generating the rotation and she sneaks that entry and that could get 70 points and if it does, this young lady will be well within the reach of an Olympic final.
Well, she was 12th at the World Cup meeting here earlier in the year.
Well, she likes this venue, likes that diving board, likes the atmosphere in this place.
70.95 for Kim.
She's the first of the divers to go above 200.
Roslyn Filion.
Not seen the best of her so far.
14th place.
As she currently stands means she would not be returning, but plenty of time to make up that margin.
3.2 in with 3.5 with Tuck for the Canadian.
Oh, it needed to be better than that.
She's just struggling with the ventries today.
You can see lots of the divers in Roslyn there with huge risk support because of the impact into the water.
And really, she needed to be cleaner in, just going loose through the body as she goes in, throwing up a load of splash.
It will get sevens, maybe less because of the amount of splash, and she'll still be struggling.
You can see, yeah, couldn't quite get the hands together to punch that clean entry into the water.
She knows what she did wrong.
Normally when she's performing well, there's a big broad smile on her face.
It's just a grimace and facial expressions probably tell you all you need to know about how this competition is unfolding for her.
Sixty-four doesn't really cut it.
She needs to be looking at seventies and sixty-one, sixty-one, sixty-four so far.
Maria Curio of Germany.
Down to the 2.8s now, so she's not going to make up much ground with this, and this is absolutely perfect, an inward 2.5 somersaults with pike.
Oh no, she's way over, way over.
The inward 2.5 in the pike position, important that you move away from the diving, but we saw Nakagawa hit her toes on this dive.
No mistakes here for Maria.
Moves away.
Oh, no, she does.
She hits the diving ball, but I didn't notice that.
I bet she does land flat on her back.
Maybe that was the reason why.
So the judges are penalized because of the entry into the water.
Yeah, just tipping her toes slightly there.
Not quite a big donk like Nakagawa, but it was just a little scrape.
Big donk in terms of the score, though.
Thirty three point six zero fours count towards a total.
That's a meager one.
and that will drop her right down.
She wasn't in the top twelve anyway and she's going to be even further adrift now.
Kim Jin Ok of the People's Republic of Korea, twenty-one year old.
She was a semi-finist in Beijing and at the last two world championships.
So, she's emulated that and at the moment, she's on course to go to the final.
Back three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
Top degree of difficulty three point three.
Oh no,
It wasn't so good in training.
I was watching.
This is always going to be the bogey dive for her.
I think that's going to put pressure on her making it through to the final.
Just waiting too long in a shape as you can see that over vertical loads of splash coming up.
She'll get penalized heavily from the judges and she has some work to do on her two remaining dives.
We're down among the very low marks at the moment.
33 followed by 44.
Only four point fives on a high tariff dive and that's going to put a big dent in her hopes of coming back.
Now onto Brittany Viola who missed the whole of 2010 recovering from two foot surgeries.
They really are patched together and just held together with bits of string and bits of plaster sometimes on these divers, especially on the ten meter board.
Here she is with her inward three and a half somersaults with three point two.
Just outside the qualification places in thirteenth.
Oh and that might not move.
Well, that definitely won't move up into
Just needed to be a little bit more confident on the exit of the dive there.
The takeoff is good.
She squeezes in tight, just comes out a little bit too early and then enters the water with the backside sticking out, which is incorrect.
You need to be completely vertical, so you need to straighten out a little bit more.
Wow, that's not even going to get over 50 points, I don't think.
Super slow motion just showing you there that she isn't quite completing the dive.
49, follows a 44, follows a 33 and at the moment the judge is not seeing what they want and the dive is not performing the way they want either and there's a big shake-up going on in the pecking order.
Espinosa Sanchez reversed three and a half, 3.3 with tuck
Oh it's better that's she is the only diver doing this dive in the competition a reverse three and a half it used to be 3.4 degree difficulty but now it's only 3.3 and I disagree with that downgrading I think Fina have got it completely wrong there this is super tricky you only ever see the men perform this dive Espinosa showing her class here but not nailing it
Wow.
Will we see a shock?
Are we seeing a shock?
Is she going to make it through?
Well, fifty-six point one zero doesn't indicate she will and she's got two more rounds to get this right and to turn it around and she's giving herself an awful lot to do.
Here me back of Italy.
Back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists currently in seventeenth
Yeah, it's one of her better dives, the 3.2.
Yeah, the back two and a half somersaults with one and a half twists.
You'll see lots and lots of girls using this this morning.
Here we go.
Generating the rotations, swinging the arms, wrapping into the twist.
This is a twist group of dive here.
Most of the girls will use this dive this morning.
They just choose to use it at different times.
You can place your dives in any order you choose to.
So it's often a game of tactics.
When do you use your best dive?
When do you use your weakest dive?
So,
Back to you with still some work to do after a poor second round dive.
Whoopee, we're into the 70s at last.
We've waited a while for that.
72 for Baki.
And with everybody else faltering, it does move her up a few spots.
Getting closer to qualification now.
Yulia Prokopchuk of Ukraine back two and a half.
Only 2.9 on this.
Oh it's pretty good, a little bit too much splash being thrown up but it's very neat and tidy, 2.9 degree of difficulty lower than what we've been seeing so it needed to be good.
This young lady's going very well this morning, one of the few actually, beautiful pike shape, great toe point just tipping over there as she went into the water so probably maybe a couple of sevens
see how mean the judges are but she does go over so I'm not sure.
I think the judges get a bit fed up with this you know.
Six point fives rather than sevens.
Just waiting for somebody to set light to this competition and really make us in theaters.
We've seen some good diving of course by the Chinese but outside of that.
Robin from Australia.
Indeed.
Very good.
To be fair.
That's right.
We've had two but the majority of divers are finding it really hard this morning to get going now.
in Shanghai World Champs, fourth in Rome.
In with three and a half somersaults with Tuck, 3.2 for the Canadian currently in fourth place.
Yep, she sneaks it in as the coach Arturo Miranda showing his appreciation because it's all about being consistent and this young lady, that's three out of three for her.
Yeah, it's a little low on the water, but she still gets in.
Seven and a halfs, I think, coming her way.
Just showing the ankle snap there on the takeoff in order to generate the rotation.
That's a lot of dive to fit in.
It's three point two.
Yeah, another day.
70.40 wouldn't be that special, but today it pretty much is because nobody's getting into that kind of echelon at the moment.
Now, welcome to the Katie Bell chat show.
Have a little chat to herself, a little chance to herself.
The reposition of the feet about ten times.
Now the inward three and a half to follow.
The tuck 3.2 for the 24 year old American.
oh wow so first two were good and the third one which she actually did a great job in the prelim she's made a mistake oh she's a bit near the diving board and then maybe she knows she is so she hangs on way too long look at that huge wave back towards
The diving board there showing that she's over rotated.
That's going to be super low thirties.
Yeah.
I think we're a little sport with the men's three meter the other night.
I think we expected the level to continue and it just hasn't with the women so far.
Maybe the final is where things will really take off.
None of these divers are taking off the way they want.
Thirty-five point two zero and she may not be returning tonight.
It's a battle of those who who don't want to make it
up to the top of her range, 3.3 back, three and a half somersaults for the Japanese.
Oh my, is having a very, very tough day out there.
How frustrating.
She is a very good diver.
She's a superb and terrific dives from her in the preliminaries.
One of the few who are shining, hitting her feet on the first dive and that has completely thrown her forward three and a half last round was mediocre.
and this one as well.
Her most difficult dive.
The backward three and a half in the tuck position.
Very poor indeed.
What a shame for Nakagawa.
She's a great diver and she will definitely not be going through to the final.
That's three poor dives.
Oh my, oh my.
Forty-two point nine zero for Nakagawa.
Yeah, she's not giving herself really much of a chance of making it through.
Other people faltering, but she's faltering probably more than most.
Russia for three and a half you get to get on with it.
Oh Yeah, you can see why she wants to get her dives done.
That's three out of three for the 23 year old from Russia Some some good diving last night finishing in the business end of the field and I'm pretty sure with another two dives of this standard she will continue to move at the pack and
She won an Olympic medal all the way back in Athens.
Very, very young then with her partner in the synchronized 10-meter.
And here she is, her third Olympic Games.
Yeah, 67.50.
That's by the standards of this morning.
Pretty decent.
And that will put her for the time being at least at the top of the pile.
Second in Shanghai.
Winner in Sheffield.
You may have seen her last year in the Grand Prix event up there.
16-year-old Hu Yudan.
and it's arm stand time everybody hold your breath double somersault one and a half twists free position
Well, that's more like it from who you Dan.
Still throwing up a little bit too much splash for my liking but the entry into the water was vertical.
I'm just used to seeing this young lady or young 16 year old dive so much better than this.
This will get eights but I've seen her score nines and upwards on this and all is missing on that is the splashless entry and I'm surprised.
I haven't seen her go into the water completely clean as yet in this competition or in the preliminaries.
That means two medals are up for grabs if who doesn't up her game to what she can do.
Chen Yulian at the end looks pretty untouchable though at the moment.
Yeah, doesn't she just.
8.0 for Hu Yudan.
76.80, coach is sending a chat, going over the dive and the pupil is taking it all on board.
Melissa Wu, sixth in Beijing in the World Championships in Rome in 2009.
Back three and a half somersaults, 3.3 in the comfort zone at the moment in position eight, but we've seen what can happen to the others.
Oh, well done, Melissa.
There's Matthew Mitchum, Olympic champion from Beijing in the platform event.
Cheering on, whistling away at Melissa, and she's done very well there.
The takeoff is weak.
So she has to wait and wait and wait, and then she pops out at the right time.
Very neat, little bit short vertical.
She'll probably sneak sevens from the judges.
And that's a good effort, especially when those around are losing their heads and faltering like a heist of cards out there.
Again, like the prelims.
Yeah, solid sixty nine point three.
Exactly like the prelims.
It's with obviously fewer competitors this time, but they're just following on where they left off last night.
Now, the very impressive today, sixteen year old Brittany Broban.
And she's going to go for the arm stand as well, falling off the back of her Australian colleague.
Seen this a few times already.
3.2 degree of difficulty on the arm stand back double somersaults with one and a half twists.
Oh, great technique.
Very, very strong on the takeoff and she backs it right up with another nailed entry.
We're looking for splashless entries and the judges are going to award that very highly indeed.
Wow.
What an impressive performance.
If this young lady continues to dive like this and she can replicate this in the final.
Well, I'm going to put my money on her for a medal.
How about that?
I'm going to go out on a limb.
I'm with you.
get some good odds for us.
We're all uh we're not allowed to bet because we work for the BBC but you know what I mean.
Seventy-six point eight zero.
You can have a sportsman's bet if you like.
Like going back to school, isn't it?
Probably actually old enough to bet.
Okay.
Seventy-six point eight for Broban.
Takes her twelve points clear.
Now, Kristen is going to go for the same thing.
Can she get anywhere near the
So, coming back tonight for the semis.
Oh, again, yeah, going from strength to strength as she did in the polymeries.
It's that weak first round dive, but this, again, still a little bit.
You know, well, she struggles on the takeoffs.
And this one is, well, it's actually OK.
But you see it finishing quite low to the water.
And she somehow manages to sneak a rip entry.
And that could get a seven and a half, which, because of the degree of difficulty, 3.2 should go over 70 points.
And that's a good score.
Anything over 70 this morning is very impressive, because it's been a rarity.
And 72 it is.
Now, Pandala Pang.
Here come all the armstands in a rush.
Exactly the same one.
I'd say we do go up to 3.3 on some of the armstands, but Panzer are not trying to cram it all in.
Just going for the slightly easier, and that's all relative of course.
Back double somersault with one and a half twists, currently in fifth place.
Well, you're getting to see like for like here.
So the previous, you know, three divers now, including Pandalina, have performed this, and Shenmue Lim will perform it after as well.
So it's really nice to see the slightly different elevations that the girls are getting from their, you know, take-offs.
Pandalina, they're just cranking the dive a little bit too much, a little bit too much rotation here, which means that she rolls over a vertical, which is a shame.
because if she'd have just popped it up a little bit higher then she'd have had more control on the entry but still very consistent today.
70 points a dive.
That's what the coach is instructing her.
Obviously too late for this round but that's what she needs to do tonight when surely she will return.
She's currently in fifth place but the class act and she was so far ahead of the field last night it was untrue like she was in a completely different competition.
The Olympic and world champion Chen Ruolin
Now, 19, 20 later this year.
Armstand back double again.
Oh, yep, just, well, almost completely ripped entry.
Just throwing up a little bit too much splash.
Great takeoff.
Very, well, super control.
One and a half twist.
Double somersault.
In she goes.
Extending a lead with that one.
I'm sure she'll get close to 80 points.
Fantastic third round dive from Chen.
Well, I'm tempted to say put the gold medal around her neck now, but obviously you have a final to come yet and five more dives this evening and things can go wrong as we have seen this morning.
But she's been on top of her game when others have been faltering and she has a lead of nine points over the rest of the field.
So after round three, two more to come.
Five rounds in women's, six rounds in men's.
We are looking for the top 12 to progress to the final tonight, and all nine of them are there so far.
Let's see those who are scrapping for the minor places, Rosley and Filion in 11th.
So we're gonna lose Batki, Viola.
We are gonna lose Paolo Espinosa-Sanchez.
That's a huge surprise.
Really is.
If she doesn't make it, Katie Bell as well, who
Had a really good sequence of dives last night, so a couple of big casualties on the way.
And a lot of those divers locked into their music, locked into perhaps their emails and their Twitter accounts.
Just trying to take themselves away.
Now onto round four of the Women's 10 meter platform semifinal.
Top twelve to progress at the moment.
is doing just that.
She's ninth place going into a penultimate dive which is the back three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
3.3 is the degree of difficulty on the opening dive of round four.
Oh, you could prove to be critical.
Kim, of course, nailing three out of three.
And she hasn't completed the dive.
Landshort to vertical.
And that could see her missing out on a place in the final.
That's a real shame.
You know, 63, 67, and 70.
And she's going to be nowhere near that with the marks on this one.
What do the judges say?
41.25.
How to undo a great sequence of dives in one fail swoop.
Must be in the lead for the time being, but she's not going to stay there for very long.
We'll go hurtling down the standings.
There's no margin for error for Rosaline Fillion either of Canada.
And this is the slightly more detailed, if you like, arm stand.
3.3.
Just trying to get it together.
There's a triple somersault on the back of this.
Oh, she's waited until now to stake her claim.
She was in 11th after the third round, so this needed to be good.
This is her highest degree of difficulty, equal highest, 3.3.
So armstand flicking, there we are.
Strong flicking, so she's just holding on to the top of her kneecaps there, but that's the first entry that she's almost got on this one.
That's going to get 7s and 7.5s, which means with a degree of difficulty of 3.3, she'll be over 70 points.
And as Bob has mentioned, anything over 70 points will put you well in contention for making a spot in the final.
Yeah, so provided nothing goes terribly wrong in the last round, she should be there.
74.25 for Roslyn, a 25-year-old from Canada.
Not been Maria Curio's day from Berlin.
22-year-old, going over the back, two and a half somersaults.
Back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists.
Lots of the girls will be finishing on this dive.
You'll see this dive from a lot of the competitors in the last round.
Here Maria, epting to use this one as her fourth round dive.
And unfortunately for her, not working very well today.
Entering the water short there.
You can see the splash being thrown back towards the diving board.
Have a look at the strain on the face of the divers as they're battling against gravity.
and different forces trying to pull them in different directions all in a fraction of seconds.
Incredible.
What kind of mark?
52.80.
I'm afraid her chances of coming back tonight look very remote at this stage.
Kim Jin Ok.
her time to do the arm stand.
It's slightly different on this.
Do you remember this from yesterday, Bob?
This is one where she placed her nose on the end of the platform.
I wonder if she's going to do the same again.
Yeah, she got very close.
Yeah.
Three point one.
It's a forward double somersault one twist.
See how close she gets today.
Yeah, right on it again.
Yep, she just, well, interesting technique.
She almost places her nose, well, she does place her nose on the towel on the end of the platform and then flicks forward with the legs in order to generate the forward rotation in order to then come out of the forward rotation into the twist and then into the pike shape.
Such a challenging dive and an interesting, here we go.
Oh, forehead on the board.
It's like a head spring in gymnastics.
Yeah, no wonder she has a towel there.
That can't be very pleasant at all.
We are seeing some different techniques, aren't we?
Some very individual interpretations of some of these dives.
And in her case, it produces a sixty five point one zero sevens across the board multiplied by the degree of difficulty.
That's how you arrive with the marks.
Remember those marks with lines through do not count.
Only the ones that don't have lines through do.
now Brittany Viola your chance to step up here and it's not a dive that's going to help you do it greatly 2.9 low tariff back two and a half oh yeah you see a lot of splash being thrown up as Bob mentioned 2.9 puts the pressure on the diver to really execute the dive superbly well and Brittany does well she does a good job here
all looks good so far all she needed was to disappear and instead she just tips a little bit over throwing up quite a bit of splash I don't think we're gonna see Viola progressing unless of course she can do a nigh on perfect last round dive but anyway anything can happen in this competition
that.
Don't let me get.
Don't let me get ahead of myself.
In fact, I'm going to take back my last statement and let's wait and see.
Fifty-two point two zero.
I'm really not what sure quite what to say about the next competitor because whatever I say has an adverse effect on her performance.
So, all I will say is here's our Espinosa Sanchez and in with three and a half.
That should do, shouldn't it?
Well, I think she dives so much better when you just keep quiet, Bob.
So I'm not sure what to make of that.
But Paola was in 15th after the third round.
This is much more like it.
This is how we're used to seeing a dive.
And this still could be better, but I'm just going to let that go and say that's great.
It'll get seven and a halfs and normally more custom to eights and 8.5s and upwards, but a little bit over for that.
So here we are.
7.5s as predicted.
72 needs to be better to make that comeback though.
And she does do it best when I say nothing at all, doesn't she?
Definitely.
Noe Batki of Italy, formerly of Hungary.
That's where she was born, in Budapest.
And she will go in with three and a half somersaults with Tuck, 3.2, currently in 13th place.
So work it out for yourself.
Get this right.
She could leap a place or two and be back for the final.
Oh yeah, that's certainly going to help her campaign.
Just on the cusp, 13th and 3.2 big degree of difficulty.
She's got a low degree of difficulty to finish on, so she knows the pressure was on this dive, her fourth round dive.
You've seen this a few times before.
This is the inward three and a half and that's going to get mid 70s.
And if it does, it gives her a really strong chance, provided she nails her last dive of going through, which would be a superb achievement for Naomi.
There are a lot of provisos today.
There's a lot of caveats from us.
76.808 across the board.
76.80.
That's very nice work by Naomi.
Up into second.
Iulia Prokopchuk of Ukraine.
We're seeing a lot of the
Fourth round dives being arm stands.
Here comes another and it is the very highest tariff 3.3.
She had problems with this last night.
Arm stand back triple.
Well, such a shame really because the takeoff was superb, the rotation was fast enough and then maybe she just fell asleep halfway through because she wasn't ready to come out of the dive and then comes out way too late.
Over she goes.
That's going to get five and a halfs and sixes.
I think she's got enough of a buffer to keep herself in contention to qualify.
She'll have to do some work on that this afternoon.
before the final, but this young lady's done very well this morning.
Some of them haven't, but Ulia has.
Strong start, just taining off a bit here.
56 followed by 54.45 for Pregopchuk, but she's up into fourth place for the time being, and that should at the moment be good enough to see her through, but it's one more round still to go.
armstand time and again a 3.3 exactly the same armstand back triple somersault for Megan Benfita having a much better semi-final than the preliminary and fourth in Shanghai fourth in Rome how much would she like to go one better in London
Yep, well I'm sure, well the thing is people need to make their way through safely to the final then you can start to turn it on.
Megan is being consistent and that's all she needs to do.
That'll put her top of the field so far.
Still some divers still to come.
This is it, 3.3.
She gets into a really good tuck shape.
Just a little bit over as she goes into the water.
So the judges all give her sevens, yep.
Yeah.
Sevens across the board.
Sixty-nine point three zero for the marks that count.
I'm going to miss Katie Bella.
She doesn't make the final and looks like she's not going to the way things are standing but she has two more rounds and she can as Leon often says, land on her head which is a good terminology, a good expression and she could be back but she's got some ground to make up.
Smile seems to have disappeared.
The concentration is still there though.
Back three and a half somersault with a count in on a three point three.
Oh, I think it might be all over for Katie Bell.
What a shame because, yes, Paul first two dies in the preliminaries and then three blistering dies to finish under this spot comfortably.
And now this is her biggest dive.
Three point three.
Just turning into Banana Woman as she goes in there.
Lower back arch.
Look at the strain through all the body in order to generate the rotation.
It even looks very quick in slow motion.
You really know how quickly these divers are moving loose as she goes into the water.
The impression of a banana and all the judges.
Well, mixed bag five and a half to six and a half.
So she's actually got away with that.
I think subconsciously you're putting forward some pilot ideas to TV producers here.
Banana man.
Would he win by the skin of his teeth?
Here's Nakagawa, reverse two and a half.
Well, Nakagawa has just gone, unfortunately, from bad to worse for her.
You know, an unsteadying start, hitting her feet on the platform, and then since then it's just been a shambles for her.
We've seen it a couple of times where divers lose the plot, and we're seeing it here with Nakagawa.
Just can't find her flow at all today.
One more dive to go.
Such a shame.
I expected this young lady Mai to be in the final, but no final for Nakagawa today.
doesn't look like it does it 18th place and tailed off at the back of the field so the sim is the best she will be able to achieve in london not the same for julia coltanova fourth place here comes her 3.2 degree of difficulty dive tuck position for the in with three and a half
well this is one that she faulted on in the preliminaries yesterday evening and it's much better job this morning in the semi-finals it's still not where it needs to be she's a little bit low on the water and then she kind of does a double come out so she comes out from the hips and then straightens the knees it should all happen simultaneously so the judges
really penalized her in the prelims for it but it was more apparent then this one is actually okay so she might get six and a halfs and sevens if she snaps out straightening through the knees and the hips at the same time it looks a lot neater and she'd probably get eights but here sevens today I predict.
A look back at the scoreboard tells her that 67.20 is her mark sevens will count and yeah she's in the comfort zone in second place there's still a few to go
Hu Yudan and her back three and a half somersaults, 3.3 with tuck.
Wow, what are we watching here?
No, Hu Yudan certainly hasn't found her rhythm or certainly hasn't found her
terrific diving that we're used to seeing.
I'm not sure whether she's injured.
She, you know, no one's made any statements, but she is diving under par.
She was definitely going to make it through to the final.
No doubt about that.
But those other medals are wide opening.
If Paolo Espinosa goes out as well, then we could be entering an interesting top three.
Yeah, five point fives.
That's a rarity for Chinese divers at any competition, and she just hasn't really got it together.
Seventy six in the previous dive was OK, but fifty four is not.
Now Melissa Wu of Australia.
Seventh place with two more dives to come in with three and a half with tuck.
Very good.
Very steady this morning from Melissa.
In with three and a half.
Such good shapes.
Knees are together.
Toes are pointed, bending at the hips and at the knees.
A little short as she went in.
That'll get seven and a half.
Not quite upright enough for an eight.
Look at that.
Perfect shape in the air.
Just a little bit short as she went in, but very steady from Wu.
She'll be one of our finalists.
It looks very much like we will have two Australians through to the top 12.
That 72 has pretty much guaranteed her place, but she's actually not been anywhere near as impressive as this young lady.
16 years of age.
Brittany Brobin, second place at the moment.
Here's her back three and a half.
Well, that's the weakest dive so far, but she's a real class act this young lady.
I am super impressed.
Yeah, she knows she's let the dive over rotate there.
But wow, look at this jump double almost by board level.
She's just a little bit late there.
If she was out earlier, she would have given herself chance just to bury that entry.
It'll only get, I don't know, five and a half maybe on that because she is quite a way over a vertical and does go loose as she goes in.
However, three exceptional dives and one dive to improve on.
She's a medal in the final.
I'm going to go out on it.
She's definitely going to podium finish.
Five point five and five towards that total of fifty two point eight zero.
Christine Sturr.
Let's make sure that she's shaking a notch Sturr here.
Back two and a half somersaults with pike, 2.9 degree of difficulty.
I was about to come out with my 007 gags, but I think she's going to get even more than sevens on that.
Again, opting for the slightly easier dive.
So 2.9 degree of difficulty.
So it needed to be good.
It was good in the prelims.
And I think that's going to get a bag full of eights for that effort.
So no 007s for Stoia.
Coming out very early, pulling the dive around.
She knows exactly where she is, very experienced, been here many times.
This will be her last Olympic Games at the age of 29, and she's securing her berth in the final, dive after dive.
Off she goes, contemplating another five dives in the final later today.
69.60 for her.
On to Hanzo Pang.
The penultimate diver in round four, currently sixth.
213 achieved so far.
She's going to add to her tally with this inward three and a half somersaults with tuck.
Well, a little bit weaker for Pandadella.
Just, I think, lacking a little bit of confidence on that.
She's been attacking her dives and maybe losing control of some of them.
So this one, she tried to play safe.
So all looks okay so far, and as she comes out thinking, oh I've got less time than I thought, just enters the water a touch short of vertical.
It won't affect her getting through to the final.
It'll be a little bit lower standard than she would have hoped, but maybe she can step up a gear for the final.
Yeah, not quite confirmed yet, because we have one more round to go.
And anything that happens, we saw in the men's three meter the other day, but within sight and within touching distance of a place in the final.
I say class act, I'm not quite sure which other way to describe Chen Ruolin.
She is in a different league when she's diving like she has been the last two days.
Back three and a half, last dive of round number four.
Yep, she certainly is a cut above.
No one challenging Chen yesterday or today.
She's having it all her own way.
But it doesn't really matter.
This is an exceptional dive.
It'll go way over 80 points.
It's 3.3.
Superb.
But of course, the semi-final scores do not carry through to the final.
So Chen is actually just doing a diving display here.
And everyone starts at zero at 7pm tonight.
Well, if I tell you, she has a gap of 39 points over the rest.
That kind of shows you that she is in a different competition altogether.
It's her against the rest, really.
And the rest are not making any inroads on her.
Different ways of preparing for round five.
Here is the standings at the end of round four.
China, Canada, Australia, and ruling Benfito and Broban.
And down to nine.
Filion should be okay.
Let's see the margin between ninth and twelfth.
Two sixty plays two forty-seven.
So, should be enough margin for error built in but we are going to lose.
Kim, Sanchez, Viola, Bell,
Well, let's wait and see if Paola Espinoza comes out with a superb last dodge.
She is in within striking distance of scraping through, all to play for on those minor places.
A lot of tension.
A word that's often used, maybe overused in sport.
A lot of pressure certainly on those around the 13, 14, 15 mark to up their game, including the opening diver in round five, 13th place at the moment for
Kim Woon Hyang.
Now can she finish with a flourish back?
Two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists, 3.2.
Get this right and she might be in contention for a return in the final.
Well, get used to this dive.
You're going to be seeing a lot of the ladies using this as their final dive.
The reason being it's 3.2 degree of difficulty, and it's actually quite easy for a 3.2.
So even though the degree of difficulty is the same as some of the dives we've seen before, because of this particular technique of dive or this style of dive, one and a half twists into the pike shape.
And you can actually see where you're going when you're in a pike position.
So you look over the end of your toes, line up into the water,
Seven, seven point fives, yep.
Seven point fives mainly.
All seven point fives are the ones that count anyway.
Seventy-two is her final mark.
Now she just has to sit and wait.
Let's see where that will be good enough.
Roslyn Filion of Canada.
Third in Montreal at the World Championships in 2005.
Fourth in Rome, seventh in Shanghai.
Very consistent performer.
And here it comes again.
Now back, two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists.
Yep, consistency is key and certainly is the case for Rosalind.
A little bit off her game last night and again this morning if I'm honest, but still coming through in the end.
Moved herself up to ninth after four rounds and I think she'll finish around about that spot here in the semi-finals, securing her berth in the final.
Good final dive.
Easy to compare like for like with Kim just before her.
Probably marginally better.
How about, no, marginally worse, actually.
Yeah, 68.80.
It's all down to the judge's interpretation.
There were some 7.5s on there, but they just didn't count towards the total.
And yeah, she's fine.
Coach Happy, she'll be relatively happy.
Is that baseball in his hand?
Yes, to calm his nerves.
Okay.
So it says kind of there, because it's nervous for the coaches as well.
So he does that with the baseball to stop himself going a bit crazy.
Maria Curio has too much to do, surely, now.
Yep, too much to do.
Low degree of difficulty to finish.
Her first Olympic Games and she made it through to the semi-finals when lots of the big names were faltering.
She managed to stay steady enough last night to make it through.
Just entering the water short here.
And it's a sevens across the board finish.
You see the judges there.
Studying the divers, she accelerates by.
Drop down camera sprays on the water there to disturb the surface so the divers can see exactly where the surface of the water is.
It's a low score, 264.
A lot to think about, yeah.
As she walks away and considers what she might do with the rest of today and indeed tomorrow.
It's not going to be on the diving board for her.
Kim Jin Ok, 11th place.
Coach watches on.
She makes a reasonable attempt at this.
She will be back tonight.
Back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists in the pike position.
oh now she was in 11th after the fourth round just letting the dive go over as she went in again you're seeing a lot of the girls finishing on this dive it's 3.2 so when it's like for like it's a battle of the execution and that is just slightly off you can see the diver over rotating there six and a half sevens probably did she have enough of a buffer to secure her spot
in the final.
She'll have an agonizing weight.
Yeah, I'm not sure.
That's gonna be quite good enough.
It's gonna be right on the margins.
65.60 and we have a computer screen alongside us that shows the qualifiers.
Nobody yet has qualified.
We don't have the big queue on our scoreboard.
As they come in, we will give them to you.
15th place.
Now, could she finish with her best dive, which she's going to need to do?
have any chance of making the top 12.
15th at the moment for Brittany Viola.
Hasn't replicated what she did in the prelims so far.
Back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists.
She's giving it a good go That's one that's probably her best dive today mom and dad Supporting her as always.
I'm sure many people behind her here made the trip to London Anyway, trying to finish with the flourish here.
I don't think that's gonna be good enough It's only gonna get sevens and seven point fives, but she would have really needed nines to To get a total worthy enough in this field to get into the final such a shame and
expected to see Viola go through this morning.
It just goes to show what can happen.
It looks like both Americans are going to go out here which is a bit of a surprise.
Seventy point four zero and her race I'm afraid looks to be run.
Okay, you keep quiet Bob.
I'll tee this one up.
This is Paula Espinoza
for someone who's won medals at a world championship wow has she done enough when it counts I think she has
Yeah, relief from the coaches.
She has had a tough day out there today.
Hasn't nailed any of her dives.
Her fourth round dive was her best one.
And this one is of equal standard.
That should get eight.
A little bit over as she went in.
3.2.
75 points or thereabouts.
There's no guarantee, but I think she might just scrape in.
Grabbing the hands to punch a hole in the water.
Look at that super slow motion as she goes in.
You can see the feet just tipping over a vertical there.
Yeah, I didn't want to be Paola's Sword of Damocles today, so I'm quite glad I didn't say anything before that dive because she's performed her best of the day.
So I know what to do tonight now, don't I?
76.80.
And she is up into third place.
Naomi Bakke has very little room for error here.
This needs to be spot on.
Reverse two and a half.
Oh, and it is two.
Spot on.
Right on the money.
2.7 degree of difficulty.
0.5 lower than Espinosa and Viola and Kim.
So it needed to be bang on the money.
It's difficult to get higher than 65 points unless of course you nail it like Naomi's done there.
She could probably get eight and a halfs for that.
Well she certainly deserves eight and a halfs.
Let's see what the judges think.
There we are.
Look at those wrist supports, the hands grabbed together entering the water.
sixty-eight point eight five for Baki and uh that has put her in a really good place in terms of progression.
First of the qualifiers, I can tell you is Roslyn Filion.
She cannot be overtaken by twelve other divers.
So, she's made it through and nobody else has yet.
Oh, it needed to be good from
started off very well and then had a little bit of a wobble and then she's come back with a strong finish in 12th after the first four rounds again saving this one until last you've seen it before it's 3.2 it's the twisty whirly whirly one and it works for her that's going to get well over 65 points not quite as good as Paola Espinosa but she gets around the 310 mark maybe yeah then I think that'll be good enough for the final
used to like those over the toffee covered in chocolate weren't they?
68.80 for Pregopchuk and she might be back Chuck later on today on to Megan Benfito of Canada back two and a half somersaults one half twists she has moved up the rankings and is second place that's been a good progression
by Megan.
And there it is, that much favored last round dive at the back.
Two and a half with one and a half twists.
Finishes off in style.
That's two Canadians through to this women's 10-meter platform final later on today.
7 PM local time.
Already an Olympic bronze medalist last week with her partner Rosalyn Fillion.
Both Rosalyn and Megan through to the final.
Superb last dive.
And probably good enough to earn her second behind Chen.
Menfito through, Filion through, Batki through, all with Qs beside their names.
They can join the Q in the net mind on this occasion.
Katie Bell.
Very sad to see her bang out of the competition as she will inevitably will do now.
Back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists.
one more time for all time's sake the counting please oh it's a good time to finish on just arching through her back as she goes into the water going over in
over as she enters.
Here we go, wrapping the arms into the one and a half twist, folding into the pike shape, squeezing in, just arching through low about there, giving the impression the diver is a little bit more untidy.
It's a good dive to finish, but that will not be good enough to break 300, and certainly not good enough to go through to the final.
That's it for her.
No more.
Coach gives a little bit of a hug, consoling Pat.
I'm not sure his name is Pat, but
On to Nakagawa of Japan.
Back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists, 3.2.
I'm afraid 18th is likely to be where she finishes up.
Oh, she's finished with a good one.
I'm so pleased for Nakagawa.
This young lady is a fantastic diver, showing what she can do in the prelims, but unfortunately, an unsteady start to her semi-final meant that the wheels came off and they tumbled down the road, but she's managed to put them back on the vehicle now.
Nails her last dive, but way too much to do.
That's a shame for Mai.
She'll be back, 25 years old,
Will she stay until Rio?
How does she finish?
Seventy-five point two zero.
She'll be thinking, if only I could have done that more consistently, then I will be thinking about a top twelve place as it is.
Eighteenth is where she will finish.
Yulia Koltanova has to be a medal contender if she continues with this good, consistent form she's shown over the first two competitions.
Here comes the back two and a half.
Yeah, very consistent from Yulia.
but she's up to game from the semis and I think she'll be a top five finish which is very impressive from this young lady one and a half twist you know this into the pike shape beautiful toe point little short she went in there just stopping the dive a little bit early she just needed to let it come round a little bit more
So improvements can be made in between now and tonight.
Maybe she's saving the best till later.
Inspired by Ilya Zakharov standing at the top of the podium only.
How long ago was that now?
Not yesterday, the day before.
70.40 for Coltenova.
I guess I've been feeling rather responsible for this.
I'm so delighted to tell you Espinosa Sanchez has made the final.
I think she would have slept tonight if she hadn't.
On to Hu Yudan, 16 year old Chinese, to finish off her program.
Oh, she is all over the shop.
Wow, a bit of a shambles from Hu Yudan right from the word go.
I'm perplexed as to why this is actually happening.
This young lady is on the Chinese team and she's on the team for a reason and that is very under par.
One and a half twist, two and a half somersaults, short as she goes in.
and a very low score from Hu Yudan.
She follows a 54 with a 56.
She will make the final but not very impressive from Hu Yudan today.
Now on to Melissa Wu of Australia.
sixth place so providing nothing goes terribly wrong on this which we wouldn't wish on her of course a back two and a half again with pike you've got used to this dive by now is she used to it and can she finish with a decent mark oh yes she can the best till last for melissa wu she's been diving steady and matthew mitcham there whistling and jeering and cheering and so he should be that's a fantastic dive
There we go.
Lots of the girls finishing on this one and Melissa Wu showing her class, securing her spot in this evening's final with eights, I would imagine, across the board.
Well, the marks have got gradually higher.
64, 69, 72 and she rounds off her program with a 76.80 lifts her up to second for the time being behind Ben Fito and above Koltenova.
She's been impressive.
What do we say about this young lady?
16 years of age.
Brittany Broban again opting to go for the same dive the majority of divers have gone for in the last round.
Third and she underlined her third place after this.
Oh, I think she can easily.
Outstanding diving from this young lady today.
There's the support, and this crowd very appreciative of all the divers, especially the ones that are nailing their dives.
You become an expert as the competition goes on.
You're looking for the splashless entry, completely vertical, and that's exactly what this young lady delivers.
Beautiful diving, and she is my tip for a medal.
See what the bookies say, everyone at home.
Well, aside from dive number four, you know, it's been exemplary.
Seventy-one, eighty-one, seventy-six, and seventy-six again from Brittany Broman.
If she can get round four sorted, she is definitely in with a great chance tonight on an Australian medal.
And they've been few and far between at this Olympics, haven't they?
Christine Stir of Germany.
Slight variance for us.
This is the dive that most people started with in the first round.
Forward three and a half somersaults with Pike for her to finish.
Yep, not the best effort for Christine.
Running out of room a little bit.
The takeoffs do let her down a little bit.
The entry into the water is always very solid for her.
This time, however, just a little bit loose as she goes in.
Not quite straightening out completely.
Throwing up a little bit of splash.
It'll still get seven and a halfs.
Opting to use the towel.
It's just a comfort thing.
A little sprays on the water showing it dives exactly where it is and Stoia through to her Olympic final.
Yeah, she's made it through.
And the queues are starting to appear now.
Side of the name.
Still won't see if Pregopchuk has made it.
She hasn't yet got that queue beside her name.
But Pandela Pang.
has done all the good work early on, so she doesn't have a nervous last dive.
The back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists, 3.2.
Yep, it's tidy.
It's clean into the water.
A little bit rolly, so she doesn't quite straighten out completely as she enters the water.
So in my opinion, she's giving it too much beans on the start there.
Cranks up the dive.
and just doesn't quite control it properly, but it'll get seven point fives and she's definitely in the final.
And interestingly enough, Chen Ruling up next doesn't even need to do her last dive.
She's already qualified.
It's impressive, isn't it?
It is impressive and just shows how far ahead of everybody else she is.
Seven point fives and Pandela.
And that will mean that she is fourth ranked after the final and very happy to be there.
But nobody can hold a candle to Chen Ruling.
She has been absolutely mustered today.
Back two and a half, going along with pretty much all the other competitors in the last round to finish.
Wow, now you see me, now you don't.
Chen Ruling disappearing into the water and just outclassing this field.
Brittany Broband looking on there, looking at the scoreboard.
Chen Ruling way over 400 points.
She'll probably be maybe even 50 points ahead of the rest of the field and she is a class act.
What a set of dives we've been treated to and it's her gold this evening to throw away if she chooses to do so and I don't think she will.
Now what is the gap between her and the rest?
We'll see in a moment.
84.80998.5 and that is a tremendous way to finish and she's never been below 73 and in four rounds up above 80 and nobody's got even close to that.
No real expression, job done.
Obviously the gold is not yet won, but it would be a big surprise if she doesn't come back and do just that this evening.
So after the final round, round five of the women's 10 meter platform, Chen Ruolin, all of 48 marks ahead of Megan Benfito.
Then the impressive Australians today, they'll be battling it out perhaps for the bronze later.
Here's the other Chinese, Hu Yudan, down in ninth place.
And who are the other three to make it through?
Batki, Espinosa-Sanchez just did it.
And for a gopchuk, too, and missing out by 1.4 points in the end, Kim Unhyang.
And no place for the two Americans, Brittany Viola and Katie Bell, both gone, not to return.
So that's the semifinal of the women's 10 meter platform done.
Chen Ruolin, the outstanding competitor in it.
Twelve will return for the final seven o'clock British summertime here at the Aquatic Centre in London's Olympic Park.
Hope you'll be able to join us for that and see who's going to pick up the minor medals.
So I think at this stage we know where the gold is going to go from Leon Taylor and myself, Bob Ballard.
Thank you for joining us and we'll talk to you and see you soon.
Ladies and gentlemen, that concludes this session.
On behalf of the International Humanities Commission, fellow members of the National Humanities Commission, the agency, and the international corporation, we welcome you on your journey.
Thank you for being part of this event.
Have a safe journey, and we hope you enjoy it.
We have two minutes for today's conversation.